A Guide to the Records of the Tracy W. McGregor Library ca. 1929-1993
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Records of the Tracy W. McGregor Library ca. 1929-1993
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11263
ca. 14,250 items (38 Hollinger boxes; 1 oversize folder and 3 index card boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Stored off-site. Users must request boxes 48 hours in advance of desired use. Neither drop-in nor next-day requests can be fulfilled. For additional information, contact Special Collections.
Custodial History
This material was transferred from the Rare Books Division of Special Collections to the Manuscript Division on November 1, 1996.
Biographical/Historical Information
Tracy W. McGregor (1869-1936), son of Thomas and Elizabeth (Taitt) McGregor, and his wife, Katherine Whitney McGregor (1873-1954) of Detroit, Michigan (married in 1901), both developed reputations as generous philanthropists and were involved in many social causes in Detroit. Early in his career, Tracy McGregor developed the McGregor Institute, a Christian center dedicated to the assistance and rehabilitation of homeless men, which endured for forty-three years. He also developed the Provident Loan Society as a reasonable alternative to the rapacious loan sharks who preyed upon those needing to borrow money. McGregor also worked to improve the Detroit Building Code, the education and care of underprivileged children, better care for the mentally sick, and was the chairman of the organizing committee which created the Detroit Council of Social Agencies and the Detroit Community Fund. The McGregor Fund, a nonprofit philanthropic corporation, was created in 1925 through gifts of the McGregors "to relieve the misfortunes and promote the well being of mankind."
Mr. McGregor also believed in the importance of supporting education and culture in society, and after he moved to Washington, D.C. in 1932, he began to earnestly collect Americana for his own pleasure and enjoyment. In 1936, McGregor visited the University of Virginia. As a result, he considered moving to Charlottesville but was prevented by his death which occurred on May 6, 1936, shortly after his visit. Upon his death, his will instructed the trustees of the McGregor Fund to give this collection to a college or university that would maintain and augment the collection and make the books available to scholars of American history. Because of his plans to move to Charlottesville, the McGregor Fund Trustees concluded that if Mr. McGregor had lived he would have established his library of American history at the University of Virginia. For this and other reasons, the McGregor Fund presented the Tracy W. McGregor Library to the University of Virginia on June 11, 1938, and his collection is now housed in the specially constructed McGregor Room of the Alderman Library.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of records pertaining to the McGregor Library, ca. 1929-1993, ca. 14,250 items (38 Hollinger boxes; 1 oversize folder and 2 index card boxes), including alphabetical correspondence of Tracy W. McGregor and the McGregor Fund with book dealers and librarians; correspondence and essays regarding the McGregor Library Reading List in American History; files on the McGregor Library publications, including typescripts, dummies, galleys and sales records; purchase records; McGregor Special Book Fund records; binding records; agendas, minutes, and correspondence of the McGregor Library Advisory Committee; reports by the McGregor curator; copies of the will, indenture, and deed of gift of Tracy W. McGregor; Description of the Tracy W. McGregor Library; files on the McGregor Room and related topics; the McGregor Room seminars; the Mather collection; and other related correspondence and materials.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series: Series I. Tracy W. McGregor Correspondence with Book Dealers, Librarians, Etc. (Boxes 1- 9); Series II. McGregor Library Advisory Committee Papers (Boxes 9-11); Series III. Publications from the McGregor Library and Related Materials. Subseries A. Manuscripts and Correspondence re Publications from the McGregor Library (Boxes 12-15). Subseries B. Miscellaneous Files concerning the Publications (Boxes 16-17); Series IV. Expenditures and Purchases. Subseries A. Tracy W. McGregor Purchase Records (Box 18). Subseries B. University of Virginia McGregor Library Purchase & Expenditure Records (Boxes 18- 23); Series V. Topical Files and Miscellaneous Files (Boxes 23-34); Series VI. McGregor Imprints Bibliography Working Files. Subseries A. Pre-Civil War Imprints (Boxes 34-35). Subseries B. Civil War Imprints and Files re the Proposed Civil War Catalog (Boxes 36-38)
Contents List
- Series I: McGregor Correspondence with Book Dealers, Librarians, etc. 1929-1936
  - Correspondence--"A", 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Adams, Randolph G., 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--"B", 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Book Meetings 1935 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--Bookplate for McGregor Books 1933 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--"C" 1930-1936, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--Cadmus Book Shop 1929-1936, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--Clements, William L. 1932-1933 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--"D" 1929-1936, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--Dauber & Pine Bookshops, Inc. 1930-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--"E" 1931-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--Eberstadt, Edward 1935-[1936] (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--Edwards, Francis 1935-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--Everitt, Charles P. 1935-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--"F" 1932-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--"G" 1933-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--Gee, Wilson (formerly #1248) 1933 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--Goodspeed's Book Shop 1929-1936, 4 folders (Box 3-4)
  - Correspondence--Grolier Club 1931-1936 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--"H" 1929-1936, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--Hart, John 1933-1935 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--Harper, Lathrop C. 1929-1936, 3 folders (Box 4-5)
  - Correspondence--Hook, James Lewis 1933-1936 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--Howes, Wright 1929-1936 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--James C. Howgate Bookseller 1935-1936 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--"I" 1931-1935 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--"J"-"K" 1931-1936 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--Karpinski, Louis C. 1933-1936 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--"L" 1934-1935 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--E.M. Lawson & Company 1934-1936 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--Library Extension 1936 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--"M" 1934-1936, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence--"N" 1934-1936, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence--"O" 1934-1936 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence--"P"-"Q" 1934-1936 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence--"R" 1934-1936, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence--Robinson, William H. 1936 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence--Rogers, Arthur 1934-1936 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence--Rosenbach Company 1934-1936 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence--"S" 1934-1936, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence--Scroll Club Bindery 1934-1936 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence--Henry Stevens, Son & Stiles 1929, 1934-1936 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence--"T" 1934-1936 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence--James Tregaskis & Son 1934-1936, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence--"U" 1934-1936 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence--"V" 1934-1936 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence--"W" 1934-1936 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence--Wells, Gabriel 1934-1936, 3 folders (Box 8-9)
  - Correspondence--"X"-"Z" 1934-1936 (Box 9)
- Series II: McGregor Library Advisory Committee Papers 1938-1970
  - McGregor Board Meeting 1938 (Box 9)
  - McGregor Advisory Committee 1939-1970 (Box 9)
  - McGregor Advisory Committee--Addresses and Telephone 1952-1954 (Box 9)
  - McGregor Advisory Committee Meetings 1939-1946, 13 folders (Box 9)
  - McGregor Advisory Committee Meetings 1947-1970, 46 folders (Box 10)
- Series III: Publications from the McGregor Library and Related Material 1941-1970
  - Subseries A: Manuscripts and Correspondence re Publications from the McGregor Library 1941-1962 (Box 12-15)
    - Publication No. 1 Dunmore's Proclamation of Emancipation Broadside 1941 (Box 12)
    - Publication No. 1 Dunmore's Proclamation of Emancipation Broadside--Correspondence 1941-1946 (Box 12)
    - Publication No. 2 Thomas Jefferson and his unknown brother Randolph 1941-1942 (Box 12)
    - Publication No. 2 Thomas Jefferson and his unknown brother Randolph--Correspondence 1941-1946, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Publication No. 3 More News from Virginia 1677 A Further Account of Bacon's Rebellion1943, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Publication No. 3 More News from Virginia 1677 A Further Account of Bacon's Rebellion--Correspondence 1942-1946, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Publication No. 4 A Brief Description of The Province of Carolina On the Coasts of Floreda1944 (Box 13)
    - Publication No. 4 A Brief Description of The Province of Carolina On the Coasts of Floreda--Correspondence 1944-1950, 1962 (Box 13)
    - Publication No. 5 Iron Works at Tuball1945, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Publication No. 5 Iron Works at Tuball 1944-1948, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Publication No. 6 By the King: A Proclamation for Settling the Plantation of Virginia1946 (Box 14)
    - Publication No. 6 By the King: A Proclamation for Settling the Plantation of Virginia--Correspondence 1945-1948 (Box 14)
    - Publication No. 7 A Plea For Federal Union, North Carolina, 17881947, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Publication No. 7 A Plea For Federal Union, North Carolina, 1788--Correspondence 1946-1951, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Publication No. 8 Jefferson's Ideas on A University Library1950, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Publication No. 8 Jefferson's Ideas on A University Library--Correspondence 1949-1953, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Publication No. 9 Memoirs of a Monticello Slave1951, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Publication-- Catalogue of the Library of the Reverend James Warley Miles1955 (Box 15)
    - Publication-- The Discoveries of John Lederer in Virginia and Carolina, 16721957, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Publication-- The Fry & Jefferson Map of Virginia & Maryland Introduction by Dumas Malone 1960 (Box 15)
      See also the Oversize Box P-19
  - Subseries B: Miscellaneous Files Concerning the Publications 1941-1970 (Box 16-17)
    - Publications 1953-1963 (Box 16)
    - Publications--Advertising and Price Lists ca. 1953-1959 (Box 16)
    - Publications--Copyrights 1941-1948 (Box 16)
    - Publications--Requests For 1942-1962, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Publications--Requests For (A-Z) 1947-1948 (Box 16)
    - Publications--Review Copies and Promotion 1957-1958 (Box 16)
    - Publications--Reviews 1953-1970 (Box 16)
    - Publications--Sales and Orders 1950-1964, 5 folders (Box 17)
    - Publications--Sales and Orders--Unpaid Accounts 1954-1962 (Box 17)
- Series IV: Expenditures and Purchases 1931-1993
  - Subseries A: Tracy W. McGregor Purchase Records 1931-1936, n.d. (Box 18)
    - The American War of Independence, Including Events leading Thereunto Henry Stevens, Son & Stiles Catalog proofs 1931 May 18 (Box 18)
    - Bound Volume--Receiving Books belonging to Tracy W. McGregor 1934-1936 (Box 18)
    - Catalogue of Rare Americana Henry Stevens, Son & Stiles proofs n.d. (Box 18)
    - Special Order Book belonging to Tracy W. McGregor 1935 (Box 18)
  - Subseries B: University of Virginia McGregor Library Purchase and Expenditure Records 1940-1993 (Box 18-23)
    - McGregor Fund Purchases 1940-1987, 17 folders (Box 18-20)
    - McGregor Fund Purchase Lists [Annual Reports] 1948-1984, 6 folders (Box 20)
    - McGregor Special Book Fund--Account #3327 1951-1960, 9 folders (Box 21-22)
    - McGregor Special Book Fund--Account #1061 1961-1979, 5 folders (Box 22)
    - McGregor Special Book Fund--Statements from the Bursar's Office 1967-1993, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - McGregor Special Book Fund Ledgers ca. 1951-1962, 2 bound volumes (Box 23)
    - McGregor Special Book Fund Ledger 1963-1982, A27-16S (Box 23)
      See also Oversize Box M-22.
- Series V: Topical and Miscellaneous Files 1936-1988, n.d.
  - Address by Henry Schoolcraft Hulbert at the Dedication of the Tracy W. McGregor Room in the Alderman Library 1939 Apr 14 (Box 23)
  - Binding Correspondence 1941-1946 (Box 23)
  - Binding Correspondence--Atelier Bookbinding Company 1943-1948 (Box 23)
  - Binding Orders--Atelier Bookbinding Company 1943-1946 (Box 23)
  - Binding Correspondence--Albert Berger & Company 1943-1947 (Box 23)
  - Binding Orders--Albert Berger & Company 1943 (Box 23)
  - Binding Correspondence--Bennett Book Studios 1944-1946 (Box 23)
  - Binding Orders--Bennett Book Studios 1944, 1946, 3 folders (Box 23)
  - Binding Correspondence--R.R. Donnelley & Sons Company 1942-1952 (Box 24)
  - Binding Correspondence--R.R. Donnelley & Sons Company ca. 1942-1943, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Binding Orders--R.R. Donnelley & Sons Company--Mather Collection 1943-1945, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Binding Correspondence--Franck, Peter 1946-1948 (Box 24)
  - Binding Orders--Franck, Peter 1946-1948 (Box 24)
  - Binding Correspondence--Goodspeed's Book Shop 1942-1943 (Box 24)
  - Binding Orders--Goodspeed's Book Shop 1942 (Box 24)
  - Binding Correspondence--Krucraft Leather Company 1947-1948 (Box 24)
  - Binding Orders--Krucraft Leather Company 1947 (Box 24)
  - Binding Orders--Little Rock Binding Company 1946 (Box 24)
  - Binding Correspondence--MacDonald Company 1946-1952 (Box 25)
  - Binding Orders--MacDonald Company 1946-1951, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Binding Correspondence--Scroll Club Bindery 1939-1942 (Box 25)
  - Binding Orders--Richard A. Smith Bindery 1954-1961 (Box 25)
  - Binding Correspondence--Thompson Bookbindery 1946-1949 (Box 25)
  - Civil War Catalogue 1960-1964 (Box 25)
    See also Boxes 36-38.
  - Description of the Tracy W. McGregor Library University of Virginia 1947-1951 (Box 25)
  - Early American Imprints (Shaw-Shoemaker) 1962-1964 (Box 26)
  - Insurance 1943-1946 (Box 26)
  - Inventory of the McGregor Library 1938 Aug 23 (Box 26)
  - Inventory of the McGregor Library 1938 Sep 8, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - McGregor, Tracy W. 1948-1958 (Box 26)
  - McGregor, Mrs. Tracy W. (Katherine Whitney) 1938-1939 (Box 26)
  - McGregor, Tracy W.--Plaque by Marshall Fredericks 1949-1952 (Box 26)
  - McGregor, Tracy W.--Portrait 1938-1953 (Box 26)
  - McGregor, Tracy W.--Will, Resolutions of Trustees, Indenture and Deed of Gift 1936-1938 (Box 26)
  - McGregor, Tracy W.--Will, Resolutions of Trustees, Indenture, and Deed of Gift (copies) 1939 (Box 26)
  - McGregor Bookplate 1936-1943 (Box 26)
    See also "Bookplate for McGregor Books" in Box 2.
  - McGregor Books--Classification and Values over $500.00 1939-1941 (Box 26)
  - McGregor-William L. Clements Correspondence--Publication in Antiquarian Bookman 1950-1952 (Box 26)
    For originals see Box 2.
  - McGregor Fund 1937-1984 (Box 27)
  - McGregor Fund Correspondence--Hulbert, Judge Henry Schoolcraft with Harry Clemons 1936-1959, 12 folders (Box 27-28)
  - McGregor Fund Correspondence--Mays, David J. 1962-1971 (Box 28)
  - McGregor Fund Correspondence--Norton, William J., President 1956-1970 (Box 28)
  - McGregor Fund Correspondence--Patterson III, W. Calvin, Executive Director 1988-1989 (Box 28)
  - McGregor Fund Correspondence--Phillips, Elliot H., President 1979-1985 (Box 28)
  - McGregor Fund Correspondence--Thurber, Cleveland, President 1939-1947, 1968-1976 (Box 28)
  - McGregor Fund Correspondence--Wheat, Renville, Secretary 1938-1968 (Box 28)
  - McGregor Fund Correspondence--White, Mildred 1939-1973, 4 folders (Carton 29)
  - McGregor Fund Correspondence--Young, Benjamin E. 1947 (Carton 29)
  - McGregor Fund--Grants 1956-1988 (Box 29)
  - "The McGregor Plan for the Encouragement of Book Collecting by American College Libraries" 1937-1948 (Box 29)
  - McGregor Room 1937-1949, 2 folders (Box 29)
  - McGregor Room--Air Conditioning 1958 (Box 29)
  - McGregor Room--Carving 1941 (Box 29)
  - McGregor Room--Photographs n.d. (Box 29)
  - McGregor Room--Reservations 1949-1973 (Box 30)
  - Mather Collection 1936-1955, 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Mather Collection--Alphabetical Author List n.d. (Box 30)
  - Mather Collection and the American Antiquarian Society 1944-1948 (Box 30)
  - Mather, Cotton 1948-1955 (Box 30)
  - Mather, Increase 1963 and 1969 (Box 30)
  - Mather, Richard 1946-1974 (Box 30)
  - Mather, William Gwinn 1928-1950 (Box 30)
  - Mather, William Gwinn--Accession Books belonging to William G. Mather re the Mather Collection [1886-1931], 2 volumes (Box 30)
  - "Mr. McGregor's Visit to the University of Virginia" [1936?] (Box 30)
  - News Notes 1946-1964, 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Pamphlet Inserts 1958 (Box 30)
  - The Reading List in American History, including newsclippings 1938-1950, 3 folders (Box 31)
  - The Reading List in American History--Correspondence 1950 (Box 31)
  - The Reading List in American History--Essays 1950-1957 (Box 31)
  - The Reading List in American History--Inter-Fraternity Council Contest 1950 (Box 31)
  - The Reading List in American History--Inter-Fraternity Council Contest--Essays 1950 (Box 31)
  - The Reading List in American History--Requests 1950-1958, 10 folders (Box 32-33)
  - The Reading List in American History--Requests for a continuation of the program 1950-1952, 3 folders (Box 33)
  - Seminars 1947-1954 (Box 33)
  - Seminars--"The Poetry of William Butler Yeats" by Donald A. Stauffer 1946 Dec 5 (Box 33)
  - Seminars--"The Work of James Joyes" by Edwin Berry Burgum 1947 Jan 16 (Box 33)
  - Seminars--"The Poetry of T.S. Eliot" by Willard Thorp 1947 Mar 21 (Box 33)
  - Seminars--"The Poetry of W.H. Auden" by Theodore Spencer 1947 May 16 (Box 33)
  - Seminars--"Poetry in the Age of Anxiety" by Cleanth Brooks 1947 Oct 31 (Box 33)
  - Seminars--"Poetry and Freedom" by W.H. Auden 1948 Feb 27 (Box 33)
  - Seminars--"Literature and Ideas" by Rene Wellek 1948 Apr 2 (Box 34)
  - Seminars--"The Work of F. Scott Fitzgerald" by Arthur Mizener 1948 May 7 (Box 34)
  - Seminars--"The Value of Literary Study to Society and the Individual" by Basil Willey 1948 Nov 5 (Box 34)
  - Seminars--"Art and Neurosis" by Lionel Trilling 1949 Nov 18 (Box 34)
  - Seminars--"The Lion and the Honeycomb" by R.P. Blackmur 1950 Mar 3 (Box 34)
  - Serials in the McGregor Library n.d. (Box 34)
  - Special Projects involving the McGregor Library 1963, n.d. (Box 34)
  - "The Tracy McGregor Library and Its Founder" by William H. Runge, published in UVA Newsletter1963 (Box 34)
  - White, John--Drawings 1956, n.d. (Box 34)
- Series VI: McGregor Imprints--Bibliography Working Files 1965, n.d.
  - Subseries A: Pre-Civil War Imprints (Study Photostats) n.d. (Box 34-35)
    - Pre-Civil War Imprint Files n.d., 3 folders (Box 34)
    - Pre-Civil War Imprint Files--Individual Titles n.d., 76 folders (Box 35)
  - Subseries B: Civil War Imprints (Study Photostats) n.d. (Box 36-38)
    - Civil War Imprints--1861 n.d., 57 folders (Box 36)
    - Civil War Imprints--1862 n.d., 61 folders (Box 36-37)
    - Civil War Imprints--1863 n.d., 50 folders (Box 37)
    - Civil War Imprints--1864 n.d., 59 folders (Box 38)
    - Civil War Imprints--1865 n.d., 41 folderws (Box 38)
    - Civil War Catalog Sheets n.d. (Box 38)
    - Civil War Imprints in the McGregor Library Searched in the National Union Catalog and Crandall n.d. (Box 38)
    - Non-Civil War Imprints 1861-1865 n.d. (Box 38)
- Card Files with Collection n.d. (Box 39-40)
  - Mather Collection--Card Files: Author Index--Mather Family n.d. (Box 39)
  - Mather Collection--Card Files: Author Index--Related Material n.d. (Box 40)
  - McGregor manuscript shelf list cardfile created by Special collections (Box 41)
- Membership Certificate for the Trollope Society belonging to Tracy W. McGregor n.d. (Oversize Box M-22)
- McGregor Special Book Fund Ledger 1963-1982 (Oversize Box M-22)
  For related material see Boxes 21-22.
- Black and white photograph of Tracy W. McGregor n.d. (Oversize Box M-22)
- The Fry and Jefferson Map of Virginia & Maryland facsimile--Introduction by Dumas Malone 1950 (Oversize Box P-19)
- McGregor Library Records on index card removed from the small green file trays on 1M n.d., 2 trays (Othertype Card file trays 73-74)